In Bhagavad-gītā He says, “Among the daityās”,
Nella Bhagavad-gītā Lui dice: «Fra i daityā»,
means ”the demons”, ”among the demons”.
ossia "i demoni", «fra i demoni».
When [in] Kṛṣṇa’s ... [in the] vibhuti chapter:
Quando [nel] Kṛṣṇa... [nel] capitolo sul vibhuti:
the different ‘of these I am that’, ‘of these I am that’.
i diversi «fra questi io sono quello», «fra questi io sono quello».
[Among the Demons]
[Fra i Demoni]
It says, “Of the daityās, the demons,
Dice:«Fra i daityās, i demoni,
I am the devoted Prahlāda.”
Io sono il devoto Prahlāda».
So, we hear at one point that
Allora, sentiamo che a un certo punto
Hiraṇyakaśipu’s wife Kayādhu is pregnant with Prahlāda,
la moglie di Hiraṇyakaśipu Kayādhu e' incinta di Prahlāda,
but it’s unknown to the gods that it’s Prahlāda Mahārāj.
ma gli déi non sanno che è Prahlāda Mahārāj.
They kidnap her and want to engage in infanticide.
La rapiscono e vogliono commettere un infanticidio.
Have the baby born and then kill
Far nascere il neonato e poi ucciderlo
thinking he’ll be a great demon, the son of Hiraṇyakaśipu.
pensando che sarà un grande demone, il figlio di Hiraṇyakaśipu.
Nārada Muni comes and says, “No, actually this is a great devotee.”
Nārada Muni viene e dice: «No, in realtà questo è un grande devoto».
How great? We also hear in the Bhāgavatam:
Quanto grande? Possiamo anche vederlo nel Bhāgavatam:
svayambhūr nāradaḥ śambhuḥ kumāraḥ kapilo manuḥ
svayambhūr nāradaḥ śambhuḥ kumāraḥ kapilo manuḥ
prahlādo janako bhīṣmo balir vaiyāsakir vayam [SB: 6.3.20]
prahlādo janako bhīṣmo balir vaiyāsakir vayam [SB: 6.3.20]
He is listed as one of the 12 mahājanas.
Lui è menzionato come uno dei 12 mahājana.
The great,
Il grande,
dharmasya tattvaṁ nihitaṁ guhāyām mahājano yena gataḥ sa panthāḥ [Cc: 2.17.186]
dharmasya tattvaṁ nihitaṁ guhāyām mahājano yena gataḥ sa panthāḥ [Cc: 2.17.186]
The great devotees who are
I grandi devoti che stanno
delivering real, substantial religion.
distribuendo religione vera e fondata.
So, Prahlāda is born and parallel to that Śiśupāla,
Allora, Prahlāda nasce e parallelamente Śiśupāla,
who, when he is a toddler, he’s blaspheming Kṛṣṇa.
che, quando era piccolo, imprecava contro Kṛṣṇa.
We’re told, when Prahlāda went to school,
Ci viene detto, quando Prahlāda andava a scuola,
you know, the Sanskrit alphabet
sapete, l'alfabeto sanscrito
begins with ‘ka’, that’s the first letter.
comincia con "ka", questa è la prima lettera.
‘ka’, ‘kha’ … ‘ja’, ‘jha’, ‘ña’ … ‘pa’, ‘pha’, ‘ba’, ‘bha’, ‘ma’, etc.
ka, kha… ja, jha, ña… pa, pha, ba, bha, ma, ecc.
Like, we have ABC’s,
Come noi abbiamo l'ABC,
I don’t know what they have in Russian,
non so cosa hanno in russo,
but in English they have ABC’s.
ma in inglese hanno l'ABC.
Here ‘ka’, when he’d say ‘ka’,
Qui "ka", quando lui dice "ka",
his body would start trembling, he’d be: ‘k- … k- …’
il suo corpo comincia a tremare, dice: «k... k...»;
because it made him think of Kṛṣṇa.
perché gli ha fatto ricordare Kṛṣṇa.
Even hearing the alphabet,
Persino ascoltando l'alfabeto,
Prahlāda Mahārāj is so exalted in consciousness,
Prahlāda Mahārāj è così elevato nella coscienza,
that he thought of Kṛṣṇa, and he would go into
che pensava a Kṛṣṇa ed entrava in
an ecstatic swoon in front of his classmates,
un estatico mancamento davanti ai suoi compagni di classe,
whom he told, when he would preach to them,
ai quali lui disse, quando predicava loro,
kaumāra ācaret prājño dharmān bhāgavatān iha [SB: 7.6.1]
kaumāra ācaret prājño dharmān bhāgavatān iha [SB: 7.6.1]
When should you take up Kṛṣṇa consciousness?
Quando dovresti accettare la coscienza di Kṛṣṇa?
Sometimes in India they say, “Dharma, artha, kāma, mokṣa”.
Delle volte in India dicono, «Dharma, artha, kāma, mokṣa».
First you do dharma up to the age of 25,
Prima segui dharma fino all'età di 25 anni,
then artha, 25, and kāma up to 50,
poi artha, 25, e kāma fino a 50,
then retire and then maybe,
poi ritirati e poi forse,
when you are in your mid 50s, late 60s—mokṣa.
quando sei a metà dei 50 anni, tardi 60—mokṣa.
Somehow that part never happens.
In qualche modo quella parte non succede mai.
50s, 60s, 70s …
50, 60, 70 anni...
it’s going far and far, recedes...
si allontana sempre più, retrocede...
That’s not what Prahlāda Mahārāj says.
Questo non è ciò che Prahlāda Mahārāj dice.
Prahlāda Mahārāj says,
Prahlāda Mahārāj dice:
kaumāra ācaret prājño dharmān bhāgavatān iha [SB: 7.6.1]
«kaumāra ācaret prājño dharmān bhāgavatān iha». [SB: 7.6.1]
You should take up Kṛṣṇa consciousness as soon as possible—
Dovresti accettare la coscienza di Kṛṣṇa al più presto,
preferably in childhood,
preferibilmente dall'infanzia,
when you are a child.
quando sei un bambino.
That’s when you should start culturing bhagavat-dharmā,
In quel momento si dovrebbe cominciare a coltivare il bhagavat-dharmā,
Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
la coscienza di Kṛṣṇa.